<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-14T14:02:35-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A (Mostly Empty) Student Portfolio</title><subtitle>Welcome! This is a showcase of all of my work thus far. It consists primarily of personal projects and other interesting (I hope!) tidbits. All student work isn't allowed to be shared, hence the somewhat empty website.</subtitle><author><name>Jack Richards</name></author><entry><title type="html">Fun With Fractions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/13/FUN-WITH-FRACTIONS/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fun With Fractions" /><published>2020-06-13T04:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T04:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/13/FUN-WITH-FRACTIONS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/13/FUN-WITH-FRACTIONS/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-simple-program-to-prove-countability-of-rationals&quot;&gt;A Simple Program to Prove Countability of Rationals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a small experiment to enumerate all rational numbers of form &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;x/y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
utilizing a set of piecewise equations as a proof that rationals are countable. 
I programmed this in Ruby for ease of implementation. This includes a fraction class 
and simplification utilizing Euclid’s GCD algorithm. Some of the theoretical backing 
came from StackExchange, and is cited in the readme for the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project itself can be found here:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jrichards15/ruby-fractions&quot;&gt;Fractions!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jack Richards</name></author><summary type="html">A Simple Program to Prove Countability of Rationals This was a small experiment to enumerate all rational numbers of form x/y utilizing a set of piecewise equations as a proof that rationals are countable. I programmed this in Ruby for ease of implementation. This includes a fraction class and simplification utilizing Euclid’s GCD algorithm. Some of the theoretical backing came from StackExchange, and is cited in the readme for the project. The project itself can be found here: Fractions!</summary></entry></feed>